Curriculum Vitae Martin Jansen (Martin-Pieter)

Duisburg, Germany/Nijmegen, Netherlands

m.p.jansen@icloud.com

Website: http://martinpjansen.github.io

ResearchGate: https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Martin-Jansen-5

Open Science Framework: https://osf.io/crhn5/ LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinpjansen/

Research interests

My current research has a focus on political microtargeting and how platforms are able to improve transparency regarding microtargeting through the use of disclosures to inform receivers about the targeting taking place. Moreover, I investigate what this means in terms of receivers' cognitions and perceptions about the platforms as well as the sender of the message. Besides my PhD work I am involved in multiple interdisciplinary workgroups with researchers from different chairs investigating Influencer marketing, trends on social platforms and social bots on Twitter. In all my work, I try to approach these subjects from a perspective of persuasive and online communication.

Education				
2020-present	Doctor of Philosophy, Social Psychology: Media and Communication			
	University of Duisburg-Essen			
2019-2020	Master of Science, Communication Science (Specialization:			
	Commercial Communication)			
	Radboud University Nijmegen			
2017-2019	Pre-master, Communication Science			
	Radboud University Nijmegen			
2019	Post-Bachelor, Sales and Account management (post-hbo)			
	Your Ability Business School			
2012-2017	Bachelor of Commerce (Commercial Economics)			
	HAN University of Applied Sciences			
2008-2012	Secondary Vocational Education, Facility Management			
	ROC Nijmegen			

Work Experience

	Work Experience
2020-present	Researcher/PhD Candidate, Social Psychology: Media and
	Communication, Department of Computer Science and Applied
	Cognitive Science, Faculty of Engineering. Part of the Research Hub
	for Human-Centered Media and Technology
	University of Duisburg-Essen
2023-2023	Visiting researcher, Behavioural Science Institute, Communication
	Science.
	Radboud University
2020	Research assistant for the Behavioural Science Institute,
	Communication Science.
	Radboud University
2018-2019	Account manager, responsible for analytics, customer contracts, appointments with clients, and lead nurturing
	Suez Recycling and Recovery Netherlands
2018	Tutor for high-school students in Mathematics, English, Economics

Peer-reviewed articles

Dreston, J., Sümer, C., Decker, H., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.-P.,** & Ain, Q. (In development) Study with me digitally, in presence or alone? The effect of social presence on perceived learning.

Maakwijzer Nijmegen

- **Jansen, M.-P.,** Decker, H., Borchert, A., & Brünker, F. (In development). Effects of Influencer Gender on Brand Attitudes and Purchase Intention in Social Media Marketing.
- **Jansen, M.-P.,** & van Ooijen, I. (In review). For your eyes only? An eye-tracking experiment investigating microtargeting transparency, visual attention and critical processing.
- **Jansen, M.-P.,** & Krämer, N.C. (In revision). Balancing perceptions of targeting: An investigation of political microtargeting transparency through a calculus approach. *PLOS ONE*.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, Meier, Y., & Krämer, N.C. (Revision resubmitted). Time for transparent targeting: an investigation of targeting disclosures, coping mechanisms, credibility, and political attitude. *Behaviour and Information Technology*.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2023). Empty Transparency? The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements. *Weizenbaum Journal of the Digital Society.* 3(1), https://doi.org/10.34669/WI.WJDS/3.1.5
- Ngo, T., Wischnewski, M., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2023). Spot The Bot: How Users Detect Social Bots and Use Profile Verification Tools on Twitter.

- Computers in Human Behaviour, 146, 107819. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2023.107819
- Wischnewski, M., Ngo, T., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N. (2022). "I agree with you, bot!" How users (dis)engage with social bots on Twitter. *New Media & Society*. 0(0), https://doi.org/10.1177/14614448211072307

Peer-reviewed Conference presentations

- **Jansen, M.-P.,** & van Ooijen, I. (2023, September). For your eyes only? An eye-tracking experiment investigating microtargeting transparency, visual attention and critical processing. Paper presented at the 13th bi-annual Media Psychology Conference, Esch-sur-Alzette Luxembourg.
- **Jansen, M.-P.,** & Krämer, N.C. (2023, May). Balancing perceptions of targeting: An investigation of political microtargeting transparency through a calculus approach. Paper presented at the 73nd annual conference of the International Communication Association, Toronto, Canada.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, Meier, Y., & Krämer, N.C. (2023, May). Time for transparent targeting: an investigation of targeting disclosures, coping mechanisms, credibility, and political attitude. Paper presented at the 73nd annual conference of the International Communication Association, Toronto, Canada.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, Meier, Y., & Krämer, N.C. (2023, May). Time for transparent targeting: an investigation of targeting disclosures, coping mechanisms, credibility, and political attitude. Paper presented at the 25th annual 24 hours of Communication Science of the Netherlands Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA), Enschede, The Netherlands.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2022, May) *The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements*. Paper presented at the 72nd annual conference of the International Communication Association, Paris, France.
- **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2022, February) *The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements*. Paper presented at the 24th annual 24 hours of Communication Science of the Netherlands Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA), Brussels, Belgium.
- Wischnewski, M., Ngo, T., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2021, September). "I agree with you, bot!" How users (dis)engage with social bots on Twitter. Poster presented at the 12th Media Psychology Conference, Aachen, Germany.
- Ngo, T., Wischnewski, M., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.-P.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2021, September). *Spot the Bot: How Users Detect Social Bots and Use Profile Verification Tools on Twitter*. Poster presented at the 12th Media Psychology Conference, Aachen, Germany.

Invited Academic Presentations, Lectures, and Panel Participation

Time for Targeting Transparency? The role of disclosures and user attitudes. Invited presentation for a colloquium at the Behavioural Science Institute, Radboud University, November 2022.

DGPuk Panel: Political Targeting During the German Federal Election. Panel at the 72nd annual conference of the International Communication Association, Paris, France, May 2022.

Research Experience

2020-present

Researcher/PhD Candidate

Social Psychology: Media and Communication. University of Duisburg

Essen

During this occupation I plan, carry out and complete studies, teach/support teaching activities and contribute to interdisciplinary workgroups (Social Bots on Twitter; Influencers in Social Media).

2020-2020

Research assistant of Dr. B. Müller

Radboud University

Responsible for preparation, organization, and data collection of three studies: one experimental study on the influence of stereotypes on teacher evaluations in higher education that led to a peer-reviewed publication: https://doi.org/10.1080/02602938.2023.2213422, a study on the influence of non-verbal imitation on resistance in a virtual reality context and a study on the influence of attitude (un)certainty on self-persuasion.

2019-2020

Master Thesis

The effects of personalization trough augmented reality on perceived value and users buying intentions in retail.

Supervised by Prof. Dr. T. Bosse.

Conducting an experimental study on the effects of personalization on perceived benefits and perceived privacy risks and the effect of value on buying intention.

2019-2020

Research in a Professional Context (Master course)

Together with 3 fellow students, I conducted a focus group study on the

recruitment of new students for Helicon schools.

Supervised by Dr. P. Nelissen.

2017

Bachelor Thesis focused on market research on modular part-time education for the faculty of education at the HAN University of Applied Sciences. Supervised by F. Croes, MSc.

Teaching experience

2020- present

Teaching multiple courses in the applied cognitive and media sciences bachelor and master, supervising bachelor theses.

University of Duisburg-Essen

2020- 2020 Teaching a bachelor course on quantitative research methods and how

to start and conduct research to a group of first year communication

students.

HAN University of Applied Sciences.

Courses/Summer schools

Introduction to R programming, July 2022

Data Science Summer School – Hertie School Berlin

Statistics and probability for data science, August 2022

Data Science Summer School – Hertie School Berlin

Data Science: R Basics, September 2020

Harvard University via edX

Society memberships

2022- present	Member of the	Netherlands-Flanders	Communication Association
---------------	---------------	----------------------	---------------------------

(NeFCA)

2021-present Member of the Communication and Technology division of the

International Communication Association (ICA)

2019-2020 Member of the sponsor committee of student basketball association

N.S.B.V. Trajanum

2016 Member of the sounding board group for the design of the minor: Sales

and key account management for the HAN University of Applied

Sciences

2012-2017 Student member of the Sales Management Association, NL (SMA)

Grants/External funding

Erasmus+ Staff mobility, 2023, visiting research stay, two months. Hosted at Radboud

University: €5.500, granted

Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst. 2022, Travel grant: €700, not granted.

Service to the field

2022- present PhD Representative for the Media Psychology division of the

Netherlands-Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA)

Conference reviewer

Media Psychology Conference (DGPs), 2023 International Communication Association Annual conference, 2021-2023 Annual 24 hours of Communication Science of the Netherlands - Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA) 2022-2023

Certificates

Basic principles of online marketing, Google Senior Sales Professional, Sales Management Association Customer oriented phone contact, Kenneth Smith Referee (F), Dutch Basketball Association

Software

SPSS, R, Jamovi, JASP, MAXQDA, Inquisit, Excel, Microsoft PowerBI,

Languages

Dutch (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (moderate)